Helen Heffron Roberts papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Helen Heffron Roberts papers
1870-1982
MS 1410
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
The papers include correspondence, research materials, notebooks, musical scores and transcripts, photographs, and writings documenting the career of Helen Heffron Roberts as an ethnomusicologist.
Roberts, Helen H. (Helen Heffron), 1888-1985
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jane B. Brown, 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Heffron Roberts, ethnomusicologist, was born in Chicago on June 12, 1888. She studied at the Chicago Musical College (1907-1909) and the American Conservatory of Music (1910-1911). Roberts continued her studies at Columbia University from 1916 to 1919, and received an M.A. in 1919. After doing fieldwork in Jamaica (1920-1921), she worked in Hawaii (1923-1924), northern and southern California (1926-1928), and in the Rio Grande pueblos (1930). Roberts was an assistant (1924-1925) and a research assistant (1925-1936) in anthropology at Yale. She was founder and later secretary (1934-1937) of the American Society for Comparative Music. In 1936, when financial support for her work was discontinued, Roberts left her musical research, and later became a nationally known gardening specialist.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, research materials, notebooks, musical scores and transcripts, photographs, and writings documenting the career of Helen Heffron Roberts as an ethnomusicologist.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Personal and Subject Files, 1870-1982, n.d. II. Musicology Files, 1898-1945, n.d. III. Photographs, 1909-1964, n.d. Series IV. Writings, 1924-1938, n.d.
Ethnomusicology; Folklore; Music, Primitive; Musicology; Hawaii -- Social life and customs; Jamaica -- Social life and customs; Roberts, Helen H. (Helen Heffron), 1888-1985
- Personal and Subject Files, 1870-1982; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. At the beginning of the series there is one folder of biographical information on Helen Roberts, including her bibliography. Subject files are primarily comprised ofcorrespondence, but include collected materials.
  - Personal, 1934-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subject Files
    - General, 1910-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Alexander Turnbull Library, 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Anthropologist, 1923-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Council ofLeamed Societies, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Folk Song Society, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American Museum ofNatural History, 1921-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American Musicological Society, 1939, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Society for Comparative Musicology, 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Archives of Traditional Music, 1966-1969. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Aryan languages [notes on origin of], undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bake, Arnold A., 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Baker, George P., 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Balfour, Henry, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Barbeau, Marius, 1946, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Barnard College, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Beardsley, Edith B., 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bernice P. Bishop Museum [Historical Recordings of Chants and Songs from the Audio-Recording Collections Department of Anthropology Bernice P. Bishop Museum with recordings made by Roberts in 1923, has been transferred to Historical Sound Recordings, Yale University Library], 1964-1965, 1970, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Blackwood, Beatrice, 1928-1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Blossom, Fred A., 1932-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Boas, Franz, 1916-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Bombay presidency [India], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Booth, Elizabeth, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Boshko-Brown, Nathalie, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Bradford, Margaret, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Brigham Young University, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - British Association for the Advancement of Science, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Brooklyn Museum, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Buck, Peter H., 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Budge, Sir Ernest A. Walter, 1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Carnegie Corporation, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Collier, John, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Columbia University, 1916-1919, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Connecticut Academy ofArts and Sciences, 1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Cosmopolitan Club, 1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Cowell, Henry, 1959, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Crampton, Henry Edward, 1932-1939 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Dauber & Pine Bookshops, 1932-40 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Dixon, Roland B., 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Dover Publications, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Edison, Thomas A. [laboratory of], 1921-1934 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - EducationaJ Music Bureau, 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Emory, Kenneth, 1923-1927, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Emory, Walter L., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Encyclopedja of the Social Sciences, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Ethnomusicology and Society of Ethnomusicology, 1967, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Fairchild Aerial Camem Corporation, 1932-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Feuillerat, Albert G., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Fewkes, J. Walter, 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - The Folk-Lore Society, 1920-1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Gabanosa, George, 1924-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Gillisi, Frank, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Grosvenor Library, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Gutlie, Carl E., 1927-1936 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Haddoo, A. C., 1928-1932 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Handy, Willowdean C., 1936, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Hanover Institute Division, 1947-1950 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Haring, Douglas G., 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Harvard University, 1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Hawaiian Legend and Folklore Commission
      - General, 1924-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Galt, J. R., 1922-1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Hay, Clarence L., 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Hayden, Glen, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Hayden, Joseph R., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Henderson, Junius, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Herskovits, Melville J., 1931-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Hodge, Frederick W., 1925, 1931-1936, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Hokan family of languages, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Hopi Indian reservation, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Hornbostel, E. M., von, 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Hughes, Charles W., 1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Indiana University Folklore Institute, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Indians, 1922,1927-1939 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Jenness, Diamond, 1936-1944 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - John C. Winston Company, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Johnson, Guy B., 1933 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Keneki, 1924-1927, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Kennedy, Donald G., 1931 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Kidder, AV., 1915-1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Kinkeldey, Otto, 1923, 1932, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Kirby, Percival R., 1932-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Kissel, Mary Lois, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Kraus Reprint Company, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Kunst, Jaap, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Labastille, Inna G., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Laboratory of Anthropology, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Lachmann, Robert E., 1932-1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - LaFleschr, Travis, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Lahiri, Sarat, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Lecture notes
      - Anthropology, undated (Box 3, Folder 92-94)
      - Australia and South Sea Islands, North America and Siberia (Box 3, Folder 95)
      - Composition, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 96)
      - Culture and environment, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
      - Harmony, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 98)
      - History of music, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 99)
      - Language, archaeology of Europe, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 100)
      - Language instruction (includes map of the Southwest and abbreviations], undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Murphey, Edith V. A., 1929, undated (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Musee Ouimet, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Museo Argentino de Ciencias Naturales, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Myres, John L., 1935 (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - National Broadcasting Company, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - National Committee on Folk Arts of the United States, 1936, undated (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Neal, Marie, 1924, 1942, 1957, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Nelson, E. G., 1925-1934 (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Nelson, N. C., 1927-1929, 1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - New Haven Symphony Orchestra, 1969, undated (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - New Mexico Chamber of Commerce, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - New School for Social Research, 1931 ~1936, undated (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - New York Public Library, 1925-1926 (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - Odum, Howard W., 1933 (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Pennington, T. K., 1943-1976, undated (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Petit, Raymond, 1934, undated (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Phelps-Stokes Fund, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Pospisil, Frantisek, 1931-1932, undated (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Rand McNally & Company, 1929, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Renaud, E. B., 1929 (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Reuter, B. A., 1929 (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Ridgeway, Sir William, 1924, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - University of Delaware Women's College, 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Vega, Carlos, 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - Victoria Memorial Museum [National Museum of Canada]
      - General, 1925-1936, undated (Box 7, Folder 167)
      - Geological Survey, 1917-1933 (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - Vrionides, Christos, 1932-1935, undated (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - Webb, Labi1abi, 1929-1931,1939 (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Websler, Carl R., 1929-1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - Wendel P. Colton Company, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 172)
    - Wheelwright, Mary C. (Box 7, Folder 173)
    - Williams, Joseph 1., 1933 (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - Winne, Jane, 1933-1936 (Box 7, Folder 175)
    - Wissler, Clark, 1870-1947 (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Wolf, Johannes, 1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - Yale University
      - General, 1923-1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 178)
      - Angell, James R. [president], 1929-1934 (Box 7, Folder 179)
    - Yale University Press, 1925, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Yerkes, Robert M.,1925, 1932-1943 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 7, Folder 182)
- Musicology Files, 1898-1945, undated; Series II
  The files are arranged alphabetically by subject and are comprised of collected materials, musical scores, handwritten notes. and various publications.
  - Acoma, 1929-1930 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - American Indian Collection [sale catalog] (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - American Society for Comparative Musicology [meeting minutes]., 1936 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Apache songs., 1920 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - Beitrage zur Kenntnis der Steinzeitlichen Musikinstrumente Europas, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Conch shell trumpets General, 1923-1937, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Note cards (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Hawaii
    - Hila
      - Book, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
      - Desha, Rev. Stephen (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Hale. J. P. (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
      - Kahaku, Waiakea (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Ka-ouli-o-na-Iani. Mrs. (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Kelsey, Theodore (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Mika, Samuela Akoni (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Pakele, Peter (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Porter, Mrs. (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Waiki, Samuela, Undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Kaahaaina, Undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Kalokuokamaile, Z. P., Undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Kau
      - Kamakanaaina, Nahoa, Undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Kawelu, Kainoa, Undated (Box 9, Folder 24-25)
      - Keawe, Mrs. Monika, Undated (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Keli'ikoa, D. M., Undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Kauai
      - Castro, Meleana, Undated (Box 9, Folder 28-29)
      - Helela, Kamehaitu, Undated (Box 9, Folder 30-31)
      - Ho'ona', Mrs., Undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
      - Hopi'i', Mrs. Levy, Undated (Box 9, Folder 33)
      - Iakopa, Mrs. Kailianu, Undated (Box 9, Folder 34-35)
      - Ilalaole, J. Ulunui, Undated (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Iskopa, Mrs. Karlisnu, Undated (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - Kaali, Undated (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Kaapuwai, Jacob Piopio, Undated (Box 9, Folder 39)
      - Ka ha, Moloa'a, Undated (Box 9, Folder 40)
      - Kala, Waiwaiole, Undated (Box 9, Folder 41-42)
      - Kelau, Haena, Undated (Box 9, Folder 43-45)
      - Koiahi, Mrs., Undated (Box 9, Folder 46)
      - Kualo (Box 9, Folder 47-48)
      - Kuapahi (Box 9, Folder 49)
      - Kuhi, P. K. (Box 10, Folder 50 -51)
      - Makea, Hanohano (Box 10, Folder 52 -53)
      - Malule (Box 10, Folder 54)
      - Maluna, Maku'e (Box 10, Folder 55)
      - Moha. Kekaha (Box 10, Folder 56 -57)
      - Nahialua, Nahaleuli (Box 10, Folder 58)
      - Naukana, JuJe (Box 10, Folder 59 -60)
      - Pa'a, Wahineikeouli (Box 10, Folder 61-62)
      - Pa'ikulu, Haena (Box 10, Folder 63)
      - Pauole, Aiamanu (Box 10, Folder 64)
      - Tovell, Mrs. Minnie [hula without music] (Box 10, Folder 65)
      - Wilcox, E. (Box 10, Folder 66)
      - Unidentified [oli without music] (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - Lana'i., 1924 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - Maui (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - North Kohala [Rev. William Kama'u] (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - North Kona
      - Alapa'i, David (Box 10, Folder 71)
      - Kaawa, Peter (Box 10, Folder 72 -73)
      - Kailihiwa, Mrs. Kamakahukilani (Box 10, Folder 74)
      - Kaluhiwa, Keluia Kailiena (Box 10, Folder 75)
      - Kawaimakaona'li'l, Ha'o, Mrs. (Box 10, Folder 76)
      - Kiaha, J. S. (Box 10, Folder 77 -78)
      - Kihe, Kaimu (Box 10, Folder 79 -80)
      - Kuehu, Kailihiwa (Box 10, Folder 81)
      - Paiwa, D. M. (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Oahu
      - Emerson, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 83)
      - Huihui, Salomono (Box 10, Folder 84 -85)
      - Kao'o, Antone (Box 10, Folder 86)
      - Keko'owai, Sam (Box 10, Folder 87)
      - Lima, William Keahi (Box 10, Folder 88)
      - Naihe, Kaahaaina (Box 10, Folder 89)
      - Nake'u, Louis (Box 10, Folder 90 -91)
      - Taylor, A. P. (Box 10, Folder 92)
      - Webb, Mrs. Lahilahi (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Puna, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - South Kohala
      - Kalaiwa'a, D. M. (Box 10, Folder 95)
      - Kalaiwa'a, W. M. (Box 10, Folder 96)
      - Malani, Kapeliela (Box 10, Folder 97 -98)
    - South Kona
      - Iwikau-i-ka-ua. (Box 10, Folder 99)
      - Ka-ai-ali'j. Sam (Box 10, Folder 100)
      - Kahikinakao'o. H. W. (Box 10, Folder 101)
      - Kalokuokamaile (Box 10, Folder 102)
      - Ma'inui, Mrs. Pila. (Box 10, Folder 103)
      - McKeaque. D. (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Unidentified, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 105 -107)
  - International Commission on Folk Arts [questionnaire]. (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Jamaica
    - Musical scores (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - Spirituals or Revival Hymns of the Jamaica Negro", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 110-111)
  - Language [Russian] (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Library of Congress [catalogue of phonograph records], 1943, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Musical Areas in Primitive North America [by Helen Roberts, includes handwritten and typed manuscripts, musical scores], 1936 (Box 11, Folder 114-116)
  - Musical scores
    - General (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - Hawaiian, 1926 (Box 11, Folder 118-119)
  - National Committee on Folk Arts of the United States, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Parsons, Elsie Clews, 1919-1923 (Box 12, Folder 121 -123)
  - Pawnee songs, 1921-1922 (Box 12, Folder 124 -126)
- Photographs, 1909-1964; Series III
  - General
    - Musical instruments (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Objects (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - People, 1909-1912 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Places, landscapes (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Arizona (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Australia, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - California, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
  - Canada [Alberta], 1929 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Columbia-University-library (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Conch shell trumptes (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Connecticut [New Haven] (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Costa Rica (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Cuba (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Dodge, Raymond (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - England [Victoria and Albert Museum], [18-] (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - France, 1928 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Hawaii
    - General, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Hilo, 1923-1924 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Kailua, 1923-1924 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Kau, 1923-1924 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Kauai, 1923-1924, undated (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Kona, 1923-1924, undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Lanai, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Oahu, 1923-1924, undated (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
  - Hawaii and Jamaica, 1919, 1924, 1930, undated (Box 15, Folder 28, Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Hincks, Carroll C., 1964, undated (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Hughes, Charles E., Undated (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Jamaica, 1921, undated (Box 15, Folder 31-32)
  - Mexico, Undated (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - New Mexico
    - General, Undated (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - Gallup, 1929, undated (Box 15, Folder 35-36)
    - Santa Fe, 1915-1916, undated (Box 16, Folder 37-38)
  - New Mexico and Arizona, Undated (Box 16, Folder 39-41)
  - New York City, Undated (Box 16, Folder 42)
  - Roberts, Helen H., Undated (Box 16, Folder 43)
  - San Ildefonso, Undated (Box 16, Folder 44)
  - Skinner, H. D., 1952 (Box 16, Folder 45)
  - Spanish Honduras, Undated (Box 16, Folder 46)
  - Suffragettes [Maryland], Undated (Box 16, Folder 47)
  - Texas, Undated (Box 16, Folder 48)
  - White, Louis, Undated (Box 16, Folder 49)
  - Wissler, Clark (Box 16, Folder 50)
  - Negatives, 1912 (Box 17, Folder 51 -53)
- Writings, 1924-1938; Series IV
  - Ancient Hawaiian Music [typescript of book], 1926, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Articles
    - American Indian Festivals and Dances, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Basketry ofthe San Carlos Apache, 1929 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Beitrage zur Kenntnis der Steinzeitlichen Musikinstrumente Europas [book review], 1938 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Chakwena Songs of Zuni and Laguna, 1923 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - The First Salmon Ceremony of the Karuk Indians, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Integratmg and Disintegrating Effects of sound Stimuli, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Lullabies in Jamaica, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Melodic Composition and Scale Foundations in Primitive Music, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Modem Tahitian Popular Songs of Ute [transcription], 1932 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Possible Survivals of African Song in Jamaica, 1926 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Primitive Music, undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Some Drums and Drum Rhythms of Jamaica, 1924 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Song Hunting in Jamaica, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Other authors [books and articles] (Box 19–21)